<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<body xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="how_to_help">
   
   <head>How to Help</head>
   
   <p>This page provides detailed information on how the reborn site at UVic
   actually works, and how you can help improve and maintain it, either as 
   a scholar or as a programmer.</p>
   
   <list>
      <item><ref target="#report">How to report problems</ref></item>
      <item><ref target="#build">How the build process works</ref></item>
      <item><ref target="#build_yourself">How to build your own copy of the site</ref></item>
      <item><ref target="#programmer">How to contribute as a programmer</ref></item>
   </list>
   
      
   <div xml:id="report">
      <head>How to report problems</head>
      
      <p>If you are a scholar or a researcher working with the dataset, you 
      may notice problems or omissions in the data that could be corrected. You 
      can report these problems to use through the GitHub repository Issues system:</p>
      
      <p><ref target="https://github.com/UVicHCMC/BBTI/issues">https://github.com/UVicHCMC/BBTI/issues</ref></p>
      
      <p>You will need to <ref target="https://github.com/signup">register as a user</ref> on GitHub if you 
         don't yet have a login; this process is free and straightforward.</p>
      
      <p>To raise an issue, click on the <emph>New issue</emph> button, and just fill in the form with 
      a heading and a detailed description of the problem. Please provide as much information
      as you can, along with sources if applicable. If the problem you are reporting is an obvious
      typographical error or spelling mistake, you can expect someone to act on it fairly quickly;
      if it's a substantive change to the data, then we will obviously wait for scholars from the
      community to weigh in, and act only when there is a consensus on what to do. The discussion
      related to an issue will take place in the form of comments on the issue ticket itself, so
      you will be able to track and participate in the discussion.</p>

      <p>If you are not able to work in GitHub, you may also send information to <a href="mailto:jenstad@uvic.ca">Janelle Jenstad</a>. Put the phrase "BBTI Correction" in the subject line of your email. In the body of your email, provide a heading for the problem and give a detailed description. Janelle will transfer this information to a GitHub and send you a link to the ticket. (Note that reporting errors to Janelle is a short-term fix. We will need a community member to take responsibility for creating tickets on behalf of others.)
      
      <p>When it comes to releasing new versions of the site publicly, we follow 
         <ref target="https://endings.uvic.ca/principles.html#release-management">Endings Principles</ref>,
         trying to ensure that each edition of the site is clearly labelled and dated, and is 
         coherent, consistent, and complete. That means that any changes made will not show up on 
         the public site until the next planned release. 
      </p>
      
   </div>
   
   <div xml:id="build">
      <head>How the build process works</head>
      
      <p>The GitHub repository contains both data and programming code. The data is in two formats:</p>
      
      <list>
         <item><emph>TSV (simple spreadsheet) files</emph>, in the <emph>sources</emph> folder, derived from the <ref target="https://ora.ox.ac.uk/objects/uuid:19b63441-9497-4b07-903b-ec5742c44806">original database dump</ref> 
            provided by the  Bodleian Libraries through the Oxford University Research Archive (OURA). At the 
         time of writing (December 24, 2024), these files are still the canonical source data; in other words, we are making corrections
         in these files, and then generating the TEI XML from them.</item>
         <item>The <emph>TEI P5 XML</emph> files in the <emph>tei</emph> folder, from which the website
         itself is generated. TEI P5 is a worldwide standard for encoding humanities datasets which has been
         in use for over 35 years (see the online <ref target="https://tei-c.org/guidelines/">TEI Guidelines</ref>).
         Eventually, we hope to leave the TSV files behind, since, as a data format, spreadsheets are rather 
         limited and difficult to constrain and process. It would be better to make the TEI files the canonical dataset, but
         this decision can only be taken with the collaboration and approval of the community.</item>
      </list>
      
      <p>Corrections, therefore, are made initially to the TSV data. Then the TEI files are regenerated 
         (using the programs <ref target="https://ant.apache.org/">Ant</ref> and 
         <ref target="https://www.saxonica.com/welcome/welcome.xml">Saxon</ref>, and the 
         language <ref target="https://www.w3.org/TR/xslt-30/#what-is-xslt">XSLT</ref>) to 
         re-create the TEI files, and all the resulting changes are committed to the repository.</p>
      
      <p>To build the site, we also use Ant, Saxon, and XSLT, this time to convert the TEI files to 
      HTML web pages. We also copy over some other resources such as CSS and JavaScript files to 
      support the site functionality.</p>
      
      <p>The result is a fully <ref target="https://endings.uvic.ca/compliance.html">Endings-compliant</ref> static website, which 
      does not require any back-end services other than a web server to function. Endings-compliance makes the
      site relatively immune from hackers, since nothing is ever sent to the server except for 
      requests for files. Endings-compliance also future-proofs the site. HTML, CSS, and JavaScript have been working for
      decades; just as simple static websites from the mid-1990s still function without any issues, 
      we believe that our static sites will be functioning without maintenance decades from now.</p>

   </div>
   
   <div xml:id="build_yourself">
      <head>How to build your own copy of the site</head>
      
      <p>Anyone can build a copy of the site at any time, and host it on their own server
      if they wish. As the <ref target="https://www.lockss.org/">LOCKSS Program</ref> says, Lots of Copies Keeps Stuff Safe, although we like to say that Lots of STATIC Copies Keeps Stuff Safer (LOSCKSS). To run a build, this is what you will 
      need:</p>
      
      <list>
         <item>A computer running a recent version of <emph>Linux</emph> or <emph>Mac OS</emph>. (Sorry, we don't have 
            resources or expertise to support Windows.)</item>
         <item><emph>Java</emph>. Install this in the most appropriate way for your operating system.</item>
         <item>Git  (on Linux, install from your package manager; on Mac OS, use 
            <ref target="https://brew.sh/">Homebrew</ref> to install it).</item>
         <item><emph>Apache Ant</emph> (again, use your package manager or Homebrew to install).</item>
         <item>The <emph>ant-contrib</emph> package (ditto).</item>
      </list>
      
      <p>Then, if you haven't yet done so, clone the GitHub repository, then run the build:</p>
      
      <list>
         <item><code>git clone git@github.com:UVicHCMC/BBTI.git</code></item>
         <item><code>cd BBTI</code></item>
         <item><code>ant</code></item>
      </list>
      
      <p>The build process may take anywhere from fifteen minutes to an hour, depending on 
      the configuration of your computer. At the end, you should have a folder called <emph>site</emph>
      which contains around 3GB of content; this is the website, and if you copy the contents of that 
      folder to any web server, the site should work.</p>
      
   </div>
   
   <div xml:id="programmer">
      <head>How to contribute as a programmer</head>
      
      <p>If you have the skills and interest and would like to contribute programming 
      code, please do so in the form of pull requests on GitHub. Also, please note that
      you should first familiarize yourself with our working methods and principles.
      Check out these resources:</p>
      
      <list>
         <item>The <ref target="https://endings.uvic.ca/principles.html">Endings Principles for Digital Longevity</ref></item>
         <item>The <ref target="https://tei-c.org/guidelines/">TEI Guidelines</ref></item>
         <item><ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/17/1/index.html">Project Resiliency</ref> 
            (a special issue of <title style="font-style: italic;">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>), and in 
            particular <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/17/1/000668/000668.html">From Tamagotchis to Pet Rocks: On Learning to Love Simplicity through the Endings Principles</ref></item>
      </list>
      
      <p>We limit our dependencies quite severely; Ant, ant-contrib, Saxon, Jing, XSLT, HTML, 
         JavaScript and CSS should be all we
      need for this project, so please do not make PRs which bring in other dependencies: no Python, 
      no Ruby, no React, no NPM, no PHP, no Typescript... you get the picture.</p>
      
   </div>
   
   
</body>
